原视频名：The Nuclear Salt Water Rocket - Possibly the Craziest Rocket Engine Ever Imagined.
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/cvZjhWE-3zM
原视频发布日期：20210110
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello, it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
I've talked about the rocket science of the Expanse in the past.
这期视频详见youtu.be/JWZqp0QoXcw
我在过去的节目中曾谈到过苍穹浩瀚 中的火箭科学
In that show, the fusion drives are a rare thing for science fiction
在那个节目中 核聚变发动机是科幻小说中罕见的东西
in that they are actually sort of within the laws of physics
因为它们实际上是符合物理学规律
albeit likely beyond any technology that could be developed soon or possibly ever.
尽管很可能这技术开发不出来
In the TV show the spacecraft have engines that are able to provide powerful thrust
在电视剧中 航天器的发动机能够提供强大的推力
comparable to the chemical rockets that we use and to launch rockets into space
可与我们使用的化学火箭相媲美 并将火箭发射到太空
but they're able to operate for days or even weeks at a time
但它们能够一次运行几天甚至几周的时间
like the ultra high efficiency ion propulsion systems used on deep space probes today.
就像今天深空探测器上使用的超高效离子推进系统
It would be really nice
这将是非常好的
if there were something that we could imagine in real life that could do both, right.
如果在现实生活中有什么我们可以想象的东西 能同时做到这两点的话 对吧
And there are smart people that have come up with a few ideas over the years
而这些年来 有些聪明的人已经想出了一些主意
so I want to talk about one particular thing known as the nuclear saltwater rocket
所以我想谈谈一个特别的东西 被称为核盐水火箭
and it's the brainchild of Robert Zubrin
是罗伯特·祖布林的想法
and you might have heard of him
你可能听说过他
because he is a sort of guy behind the Mars direct concept
因为他是火星直达概念的幕后推手
which has sort of become the basis for most of the plans to send humans to the red planet.
这也算是启发了大多数将人类送入红色星球的计划
So rocket engines
那么火箭发动机
they obviously work by sending out exhaust, reaction mass at high velocities in one direction
显然工作原理是 在某个方向把化学反应产生的废气质量以高速排出
and the conservation of momentum means that you get thrust in the opposite direction
而动量守恒意味着你会被推向相反的方向
and they need a lot of energy to throw out the material.
而发动机就需要大量的能量来抛出材料
And conventional chemical engines the combustion of the fuel provides the bulk of the energy
而在传统的化学发动机中 燃料的燃烧提供了大部分的能量
whereas in ion thrusters that energy comes from solar panels that are soaking up the sun.
而在离子推进器中 能量来自于吸收太阳能的太阳能板
So the power from those solar panels is actually pretty wimpy compared to the fury of the chemical reaction
所以比起化学反应的狂暴 那些太阳能板的能量其实是很微弱的
but both of them are much lower energy density than what's available from nuclear reactions.
但它们的能量密度都比核反应的能量密度低得多
Now there are actually nuclear thermal engines
那么其实是有核热发动机的
and that's where you have a nuclear reactor
也就是发动机里有核反应堆
and you blow propellant over it to cool it down.
然后把推进剂吹到反应堆上使之冷却
And so you can heat the propellant to a relatively high temperature
所以你可以把推进剂加热到一个相对较高的温度
and use the reactor sort of continuously with a lot of propellant.
并基本上不断地用推进剂冷却反应堆
Now this may sound crazy but they've actually built and tested these in the past
那么 这可能听起来很疯狂 但实际上在过去 已经有人建造和测试这些发动机了
in fact they did a lot of testing in a place known as Jackass Flats.
事实上 他们在Jackass Flats做了很多测试
The program to develop these was shut down.
开发这些的计划被终止了
Probably because it was a key step to potentially extending the Apollo program to Mars
可能是因为它是将阿波罗计划延伸到火星的关键一步
and government really wasn't wanting to fund something as extravagant as that.
而政府也确实不想资助这么奢侈的东西
So anyway in your nuclear thermal thrusters
所以无论如何 对于你的核热推进器
they're about twice as efficient as the best chemical engines.
它们的效率大约是最好的化学发动机的两倍
But there are limits on this because to make things better
但这是有限度的 因为要让效率变得更高的话
the reactor needs to be hotter and hotter.
反应堆需要更热
But if it gets too hot then it'll melt.
但是 如果它变得太热 那么它就会融化
I mean it won't melt down because it's in zero-G
我是指 它不会向下融化 因为在零重力的情况下不会向下
but it having a liquid or even vaporized core is not good.
但核心因此液化或者气化是不好的
I mean it sounds catastrophic, right.
我是指 这听起来是灾难性的 对吧
But there are actually ideas for gas core nuclear reactors
但实际上 有气芯核反应堆的计划
where the reactor is actually a superheated plasma containing fissile uranium or plutonium.
反应堆实际上是一个过热的等离子体 含有可裂变铀或钚
This is obviously a technical challenge but that's a whole other video.
这显然是一个技术上的挑战 但把这些放到另一个视频去讲吧
No the nuclear salt water rocket works
与之不同的是 核盐水火箭的工作原理
by having a sustained nuclear reaction in the propellant as it flows through the engine itself.
是推进剂在流经发动机本身时 持续发生的核反应
It's just like a chemical rocket which has a chemical reaction as the fuel flows through it
这就像化学火箭一样 当燃料流过火箭时 火箭会发生化学反应
but with it vastly more energy available to it.
但其可利用的能量却大大增加
The exhaust from a chemical rocket is thousands of degrees
化学火箭的废气是几千度的
but it could be hundreds of thousands of degrees in a nuclear salt water rocket.
但在核盐水火箭中可能是几十万度
So the propellant is water with a uranium or plutonium salt dissolved in it.
所以推进剂是溶解了铀或钚盐的水
The original proposal had a two percent uranium tetrabromide mixture with regular water.
最初的方案中是2%的四溴化铀与普通水的混合物
The uranium itself would also be enriched to about 20 percent uranium-235.
铀本身也会被浓缩到大约20%的铀235
That's reactor grade uranium.
这是反应堆级的铀
So in that mixture it contains everything it needs to sustain a chain reaction.
因此 在该混合物中 (这样的浓度)可以维持一个链式反应
If you get enough of it in the right place,
如果在正确的地方得到足够多的铀
you will have a critical mass and the neutron driven reaction will run away exponentially
就会达到临界质量 而中子驱动的反应将以指数级别运行
and the water will explode into hot plasma.
而水会爆炸成热等离子体
So the first problem is making a fuel tank that can store huge quantities of propellant
所以 第一个问题是制造一个可以储存大量推进剂的燃料箱
and you do this by having a lot of neutron absorbing materials spread throughout the interior of the tank.
而这样的话就要把大量的中子吸收材料 铺满整个储罐的内部
Things like boron which will soak up those excess neutrons
像硼这样的材料可以吸收多余的中子
before they can drive a runaway reaction and ruin your day.
以免反应失控 并发生意外
If you have a fuel leak by the way then you'd better hope that it doesn't accumulate in any one place.
顺便说一下 如果燃料发生了泄漏 那么你最好希望它别积聚在任何一个地方
Otherwise it will eventually react when it collects a critical mass.
否则当它聚集到一个临界质量时 最终就会发生反应
So the neutron suppression is a key part of the fuel handling
那么中子抑制是燃料处理的一个关键部分
and that has to be maintained right up to the point where you actually want it to react.
而这必须要恰到好处 该反应的时候就要反应
So in simple terms you pump the salt water down boron lined pipes into the chamber
那么简单来说 你把盐水从衬有硼的管子里抽到燃烧室去
and if you do it at the right speed
如果速度没问题
you can get a highly energetic self-sustaining nuclear reaction
你就可以得到一个高能量的自我维持的核反应
which generates incredibly energetic plasma
它能产生令人难以置信的高能等离子体
and it's this plasma which generates the thrust.
而正是这种等离子体产生了推力
This isn't like the slow chain reaction you get in a regular nuclear reactor
这不像普通核反应堆中的缓慢的连锁反应
where it's only barely critical so they can control it.
在那种反应中 它只是勉强超过临界状态 这样就可以得到控制
This is a reaction
而这种反应
where the criticality is maximized to burn as much fuel as possible before it expands into space.
其中临界状态是在扩散到太空中之前 最大限度地燃烧
It's kind of like trying to replicate
这有点像是试图复制
the prompt criticality conditions in the excursion that destroyed the chernobyl reactor
摧毁切尔诺贝利反应堆事故的瞬发临界条件
but then you keep it running at that level continuously.
但你要让它持续在这个水平上运行
Sounds fun doesn't it, right.
听起来很有趣 对吧
So yeah the water is of course key to this whole process.
所以 当然 水是整个过程的关键
Uranium at 20 enrichment doesn't undergo a chain reaction on its own
铀在20%的浓度下不会发生链式反应
because the highly energetic neutrons that come out of those fission events
因为这些裂变事件中产生的高能中子
have a very low probability of triggering another fission event.
触发另一次裂变事件的概率非常低
but slower neutrons are much more likely to make further fissions possible.
但速度较慢的中子则更有可能促使进一步的裂变
So the water basically acts as a moderator.
那么水基本上是起到了调节作用
Those highly energetic neutrons,
那些高能中子
they freshly liberated from a fission event,
刚从裂变事件中释放出来
bounce around off the water molecules
在水分子之间来回反弹
until they're moving around slowly enough
直到它们移动得足够慢
that they can make more reactions happen and sustain your reaction.
以至于可以让更多的反应发生 并使反应得以维持
And this bouncing around leads to another trick that's in play in the design.
而这种反弹会在设计中起作用
So you want to keep this highly energetic reaction under control
那么 你要让这种高能的反应处于控制之下
because of course the neutrons are bouncing around in the water.
因为中子当然会在水里跳来跳去
They actually get dragged along by the water flow, right.
实际上会被水流拖着走 对吧
They're bouncing off the water molecules and that takes time
从水分子上反弹是要花时间的
and so they end up getting pushed along.
所以它们最终会被推着走
So if the water flow is fast enough
所以如果水流够快
you can actually stop the neutrons running upstream into the rest of your engine
实际上 你可以阻止中子向上游跑到发动机的其余部分
which is probably a good thing
那么这基本是件好事
because you don't want a nuclear reaction running up inside your engine plumbing
因为你不希望核反应在你的发动机管道内发生
where you don't want nuclear reactions to occur.
也就是你不希望发生核反应的地方
Depending upon how you do the math
取决于你的计算方式
you need to get the water moving maybe at around 66 meters per second
你需要让水以66m/s左右的速度流动起来
it could be higher depending upon how you do your math.
可能会更高 这取决于你如何计算
But this is something that's sort of doable.
但这是具备可行性的
It's not like supersonic water flows.
并不像超音速的水流那样
Of course that's about 240 kilometers per hour for those that are keeping track.
当然了 对于那些还在认真看视频的 我解释一下 这大概是240km/h的速度
But yeah do that and the majority of the reaction will stay happening in the place where you want it to.
但是 是的 这样做 大部分的反应会停留在你想要的地方发生
So there's another way to think about this
所以有另一种方式来思考这个问题
and that is as a continuous thrust version of the orion nuclear pulse drive.
那是作为一个连续推力版的猎户座核脉冲发动机
That's where you take nuclear bombs and you set them off close to a pusher plate
就是把核弹放在靠近推板的地方引爆
and that pushes the spaceship along.
然后推动飞船前进
But instead you've got a continuous nuclear explosion happening.
但与之相反 这样做 核爆炸已经是连续发生的
So to generate thrust effectively you need to direct all this fire and fury.
所以为了有效地产生推力 你需要引导所有狂暴的火焰
All these exploding gases need to be directed using a nozzle.
这些爆炸的气体需要用喷嘴来引导
But with the amount of heat and radiation
但由于热量和辐射量太大
any unprotected physical nozzle would vaporize in short order.
任何没有保护的物理喷嘴都会在短时间内汽化
So the design has a layer of regular clean water running around the outside
所以设计中在外面有一层常规的清水流过
And that acts as an insulating layer
这就像一个隔热层
protecting both the nozzle from the heat and the radiation.
保护喷嘴免受热量和辐射的影响
So some numbers.
那么 列举一些数字
The paper estimates that perhaps you'd only have 0.1 percent of the uranium 235 undergoing fission
论文估计 也许你只有0.1%的铀235在进行裂变
which at two percent concentration salt, 20 percent enrichment
2%浓度的盐溶液 20%的(铀235)浓度
gives you 3.4 gigajoules per kilogram.
这样 能量密度可达3.4千兆焦耳每千克
That's about 900 times the energy density of TNT.
这大约是TNT能量密度的900倍
And that translates to an exhaust velocity of about 60 to 70 kilometers per second
这意味着排气速度约为60-70km/s
depending upon how good your nozzle is.
取决于你的喷嘴有多好
That's about the same as the exhaust velocity from ion thrusters
这和离子推进器的排气速度差不多
but in this case you're no longer limited by the tiny amount of power
但在这种情况下 你不再受制于微不足道的功率了
that you can soak up through those solar panels.
也就是受限于太阳能板提供的功率
So the sample design that was in the paper.
那么论文中的样本设计
It used an inlet pipe which was six centimeters in diameter like that size
它使用了一个直径为6厘米的进水管 差不多就这种尺寸
with a propellant flow of 200 kilograms per second through that
通过管道的推进剂流量为200kg/s
and this would generate a thrust of about 1300 tons.
这将产生约1300吨的推力
That works out to a steady state power of 700 gigawatts
这相当于700千兆瓦的稳态功率
which by the way when chernobyl reached peak power during its explosion
顺便说一句 当切尔诺贝利在爆炸时达到峰值功率时
it was about 350 gigawatts for a fraction of a second.
在一瞬间达到了约350千兆瓦
This is 700 gigawatts continuously right.
而这是持续的700千兆瓦 没错吧
It's a non-stop chernobyl going on.
这是一个不停在发生的切尔诺贝利
Now that thrust is roughly equivalent to two F1 engines that they used on the Saturn V.
那么这个推力大约相当于土星五号上的两个F1发动机的推力
Those of course to do that each required two and a half tons of propellant
当然 每台F1发动机都需要两吨半的推进剂
so if you only need 200 kilograms versus five tons that's about 25 times more efficient
那么如果你只需要200公斤 而不是5吨 那就是25倍的效率
which is a nice step up.
这是一个不错的进步
To be clear you really wouldn't want to use this as the first stage to a rocket on the ground
需要申明的是 你真的不想用它作为地面火箭的第一级
it would spread nasty radioactive fission products all over the place.
它将把讨厌的放射性裂变产物扩散到所有地方
It would make the Rocky Flats Plant nuclear facility cleanup look, well, easy in comparison.
这可比洛基平原工厂核设施的清理复杂多了
But in deep space that radioactive exhaust is going so fast
但在深空 放射性废气的速度是如此之快
that it rapidly spreads throughout space and goes to almost zero concentrations.
会迅速地扩散到整个空间 几乎达到零浓度
in fact some of it is going so fast it will leave the solar system all together.
事实上 有些物质的速度非常快 甚至会一起离开太阳系
Now if you were to say look at SpaceX's Starship
那么 假设SpaceX的Starship
and then build a version with a nuclear saltwater rocket.
换成了核盐水火箭的版本
Same amount of propellant mass
同样质量的推进剂
Starship right now in theory gets about eight to nine kilometers per second of Delta V.
现在的Starship理论上能获得8-9km/s的速度增量(dv)
You switch it up with a nuclear salt water rocket.
如果换成核盐水火箭的话
You could get 150 kilometers per second.
dv就能达到150km/s
You could travel to Jupiter in a couple of months.
几个月后就可以到木星去了
And come back in a couple of months using single fuel load.
之后几个月 同样的一罐燃料也可以用于返回
It's quite amazing.
这是相当惊人的
To people thinking about the future of space, futurists and science fiction writers
对于思考未来太空的人 未来学家和科幻小说家来说
the nuclear salt water rocket is actually pretty attractive
核盐水火箭其实很有吸引力
because there's nothing fundamentally about it that breaks the laws of physics.
因为从根本上来说 它并没有什么违反物理定律的地方
There's no obvious showstoppers that a bright student can point out.
甚至没有那种明显的问题 会被聪明的学生打断
Sure the simplistic sketch in the paper would likely to have a lot more complexity
当然 论文中的简单草图很可能会更复杂
if it was turned into a real engine.
也就是在变成一个真正的发动机之后
You'd probably need neutron sources and neutron absorbers near the injection point.
在靠近推进剂注入位置的地方 你可能需要中子源和中子吸收装置
You could reconfigure to control the reaction
你需要有能力重新配置以控制反应
and while pumping fluids at this rate isn't too hard
虽然以这种速度泵送液体并不难
there's a question of maybe how you would power those pumps without adding lots of excess mass.
但仍然存在一个问题 那就是在不增加大量多余质量的情况下为这些泵提供动力
But these are easy problems that we can think of.
但这些都是我们能想到的简单问题
Indeed it's entirely likely that there's fundamental parts of material science
事实上 这完全有可能是材料科学的基本部分
that simply can't deliver the kind of properties
也就是材料根本无法提供的那种性能
that we would need to turn a theoretical possibility like this into an engineering reality.
而这种性能正是我们所需要的 这样才能把这种理论上的可能性变成工程上的现实
But just say it could be made to work.
但只是假设 这是能起作用的
Then the same paper did the math for a more powerful more efficient version
然后同一篇论文为一个更强大更高效的版本做了计算
instead of using reactor grade uranium, it used weapons grade uranium, enriched in 90 percent uranium-235.
它没有使用反应堆级的铀 而是使用了武器级的铀 铀-235的浓度为90%
And then assumed more of the uranium undergoes fission
然后假设更多的铀进行裂变
and in that case something like this would have an exhaust velocity
在这种情况下 像这样的东西会达到这种程度的排气速度
possibly over one percent of the speed of light.
可能超过光速的百分之一
And then you'd be in the position to send spacecraft to other stars in decades rather than centuries
然后你就可以在几十年内而不是几百年内 把航天器送到其他恒星去了
So even if science delivers the ability to fly around the solar system in a few months
所以即使科学提供了在几个月内绕太阳系飞行的能力
by riding a continuous nuclear explosion,
通过乘坐这种连续核爆炸作为动力的飞船
we'll still be able to dream of a sci-fI future where the ships could go faster still.
我们仍然可以梦想一个飞船可以跑得更快的科幻的未来
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]